hello everybody thanks for tuning in
so you're getting ready for to listen on
on a real treat because the second video
is where we begin to read on the first
thing that we're going to read before we
go into the katana dialogues which is
the article that Chris and John who
Vicki wrote called it's gnosis and the
second person which I think serves to
just be if it's beautifully written I
mean so good one of those things where
it's like what it takes to to comprehend
it is enacting the very thing that
you're comprehending and that that
continual perm you netic it I think it's
a pork revelation about that and so I
wanted to just encourage you to read
along what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
upload the paper to a Google Doc and
then they'll put it below so you can
find that below near you can read along
with us if you want some housekeeping
things so in terms of events for the
circling it's a - which is which is my
company because of the coronavirus we
are going to be moving some of our
events to online so you know before you
before you drive off to the events
please make sure and check out our
Facebook page will will give you
information and how to where not to go
and how to how to get online we'll be
doing some things on zoom and it'll be
an experiment for us because we've been
such an in-person participatory company
so this will be an experiment in that in
in a way they'll keep us all from
spreading the virus
also if you are interested in coaching
with me email me my emails below and I
think that's it so enjoy the first of
I'm sure the thousand videos in the
series because it'll probably I don't
know if I'll be able to complete
complete this reading of the dialogues
in our lifetime but I'm looking forward
to dying trying alright have a really
good day and thanks for tuning in it
says right and instead of contributing
to the deconstructive project of trying
to VRS away from it yeah yeah and some
of think some of deconstruction is kind
of doing that almost perniciously and
some of it I think is more innocently
trying to grapple with problem that we
inherited so they're not all the same
but but yeah it's it's really it's just
what I met what a mess think what the
magnitude of that problem is just like
you're rushing yeah you know this kind
of visual symbol I just pressed record
by the way
okay so just probably do that from now
on because we should just probably do
that from now on yeah totally did so
exam so welcome welcome to my screen and
what did i welcome myself to your screen
and welcome to my screen yeah it's not
as blessed I would think but I've often
had this I got this thought this thought
about wouldn't be interesting to like
yeah this a prompt right and it's just a
sitcom about something right and then
all of a sudden what the characters
notices that it's on a flat screen of
late it somehow it figured it out right
so all of a sudden it realizes that oh
my god this all this stuff about
dimensions and there's me and you
there's actually just this
flat-screen and I'm being watched by
another thing mm-hmm what what would
happen to the rest of the narrative like
mmm would he would he would he be what
he would be let's kind of give
everything up and just work at Starbucks
and just be fascinated by the drip of
the coffee realizing it's everything
would he start a religion and try to
like get other people to like trick them
into seeing that their flatus would
become like it would become that's
basically sounds like a sounds like a
quintessentially gnostic quest that it
would sort of it would it would trip the
motivation to somehow to house to
somehow be emancipated from the flat
screen right it would begin a quest to
basically work your way out of the
predicament right and like and like at
one point would the character would it
lose grasp that it like would it forget
and then would it be able to tell that
it forgot right and then would it go on
the whole whole thing of like it you
know it realizing that it it got so you
know attached yeah it didn't realize its
attachment made it more right or the
illusion than thin right itself you know
it's right you just go in all these
different directions that's right one
time when I was when when Breanna and I
were home all weekend or something and
we watched you know all of the all the
matrix videos I had this idea I was like
you know be interesting to kind of play
this game of where we think about each
one of our friends and we think about
for each of them what would it take for
them to like realize that they were in
the matrix okay like what what angle
would you have to go into and it's so
funny you know it was like we still
would talk about each person's like oh
this person like what it would be so
hard for them but like why like you know
would be so hard and who would it be
easy and who
in what angle would you go into it is so
interesting how personality and
character kind of came to light and I
was like wouldn't that be a fascinating
game and brands like don't you call that
circling I was like oh I like well what
a relief to realize that you were in the
right place doing the right thing then
to add then to abstract away from you
know who and what you are in Scituate to
find yourself right back where you
started and realize oh well I want to be
doing this because this is what I'm
doing that's do you should you find when
you did that exercise together did you
find that you shared the same intuitions
about the people that you ran through
yeah that's what's interesting is you
know we talked about Bob and it's like
oh it was so clear to both of us Bob you
can never I would be would be oblivious
right just be so suspicious right or
whatever you get all these character
ology these psychological character
traits there's a lake you know and it
goes to this one the existentialist
psychologists thing that character on
some level is your project against death
your cut-rate
way of defending against dying right
that's right that's right well because
like it's true to that Heric their
attempt at Heraclitus maxim right of
character being being destiny character
being so being determinate of though of
all things i mean that's that sort of
the essence of really good classic drama
especially classic tragedy is that
there's that character predestined the
fate of of all persons right and that
the fundamental change in character for
tends a change in destiny and it's kind
of ties back to that little that little
fun exercise you were talking about a
moment ago about a character realizing
that they were on the wrong side of a
flat screen boundary and then craving
emancipation from it because it makes me
because because that is it that is a
traditionally dramatic device right I
mean right back to the Greek chorus the
idea that there is an awareness beyond
the enclosed perspective of
character undertaking the journey that
that that that whose refrain brings the
view from above right the the
perspective from without and when it
does happen and and and you know the
breaking the fourth wall as it were in a
drama can be a little bit of a gimmick
thing to do but those that do it well
there's a show they're just so right now
called the fleabag at some one of
streaming services I think it's on
Amazon anyway it's about a young woman
in London and it's just about her life
more or less it's it's been very lauded
and deservedly so because it's like
fiercely fiercely witty drama and it's
basically about a person who goes you
know from from day to day for a moment
to moment and has a constant refrain to
the fourth wall right she looks into you
as the audience but rather than that
just being a delivery mechanism for
exposition or something like that or a
way of a character being able to choose
scenery what it becomes is it becomes a
it reveals an appetite for an extrinsic
perspective to help deliver her from the
confines of her predicaments and her
ethical and moral dilemmas on a
day-to-day basis it's like a it's like
the reckless or the audience looking in
it's like the representation of a third
factor the spirit from without the
perspective that exceeds that of the
character but that this would
desperately crave and there's one
character at one point in the show who
notices and this is really interesting
who notices that she keeps gesturing
herself to that third factor that she
keeps gesturing herself outside of the
bounded world in which she exists and
that that that a character is able to
notice that about her becomes the
kindling for for for intimacy and for a
kind of mutual knowing that she's been
deprived of in her other relationships
so there's something
observant about this that that the that
day the the sort of the the beckoning of
that that that choral perspective that
exists outside the bounded frame of her
life in situ that the recognition of
that appetite is synonymous in the
narrative with a kind of recognition of
her almost like a sensibility
transcendence that occurs because of
someone noticing that deep deep deep
that felt lack that manifests as as that
constant gesture to outside somebody
else noticing and that becomes one it's
interesting it becomes the they notice
what's beyond her yes her and then she
probably feels seen yes so what scene is
what's somehow beyond her yes yes yeah
yes yes exactly there's that what is it
is we're probably gonna read in a second
yes yes what is it the Ianto it's a tomb
intimation information kind of kind of
yeah yeah yeah and so she exactly in a
certain sense in a way rations right
toward that relationship she does right
cuz that person she does the exactly
like that the after image or the
preimage almost is exactly because that
because that person's perspective of her
relates not simply to her but relates to
her in potentia right relates to a force
that verbalizes her from without that
that remains in the margins of her
possibility and that is what the person
starts to attend to which is true of our
close and intimate relationships even
friendships right do that as well if
someone sees you for what you you
can become yeah in addition for who you
are by by constraints of your necessity
then already that means that the
affordances of that relationship are
multitudinous they amount to much more
than what you are in the confines of
actuality at any given moment which is
how you know you have something really
valuable between you yeah so it's so
interesting because I've always had that
sense of people talk about encircling
they talk about this experience of being
deeply seen and like in kind of in being
deeply see and they recognize the rarity
of how scene deprived they've been but
I've always had this sense of like you
know scene seems to constitute this kind
of sense of like there's there's
something that you are and that it has
not been visible to anybody and then you
see it right but actually I never know I
it's net it's that's not the experience
of being seen on some level there's
sense in which the thing it's almost
like the very thing it's almost the
reason why you do anything at all right
that's actually concealed in its comings
and goings and what people relate to
it's been it's being related to like oh
I see what you couldn't have seen in
yourself but you see it in the moment
that I say it that has been the thing
that has pulled you forward and then I
feel see it's very very hmm it also has
then because because then the the the
the partners in the process become
conspirators for its police' second
spire to pronounce it to reveal it to
bring it forth and and and to be to be
like they become causative of it in a
way right even though it even though it
lay already in the offing of possibility
in that conversation they called it
forth they helped to verbalize it he's
kind of getting me it's it's interesting
because there is this quality and this
is one of the things that the the
circling practice has been like you
struck me about
what how people really consolidate when
that they went out which is unseen is
coming to be seen there is this quality
where everyone is drawn in it's almost
like they have to say it like everyone's
drawn almost like uh it's almost like a
kind of strange kind of prayer in a way
right in Clara t'v sense that everyone
goes into this sense where you're
looking at something and and like it's
like there's this thing that's just out
of concealment right and it must be
there's like a month BC said yes oh yes
and yeah exactly exactly and no it needs
us to be is to be informed with the
proper attention I mean it reminds me of
the it reminds me of the famous the
famous metaphor that Platanias uses for
sculpture right that that the treatment
of one's soul that the crafting of one's
soul and the the the gilding of the
matter of the person with form is as the
process of sculpting marble because what
you're ultimately doing is you're you're
at least phenomenologically are working
to pronounce something that it's already
there but concealed by its matter and so
you're we're working you're
collaborating in the process of
informing the matter and and and of
course we can do that
interior lee there's a process in which
and that is a dialectical and dialogic
process which maybe will segue into the
chapter but that's a dialogical process
of pronunciation of the form that's
there concealed beneath the concealed
beneath the forgetfulness concealed
beneath forgotten and so that that that
process of sculpting the process of the
Kratt the technically of the soul as it
were is an interior process but of
course it's also trained and conditioned
by the exterior dialogue and dialectical
processes that we have between us so
we're we're we're we're Co sculpting in
addition to sculpting each each in his
own
Jiri hora t huh to animate bit there's a
there's a chiasma they cross to those
two processes intersect and the point at
which they intersect is the point to
that's that's the horizon of
intelligibility that's retreating away
as we burrow more closely into ourselves
and more closely into one another yeah
that yes that horizon of intelligibility
that's retreating always we burrow into
what's most close to us that's the I
mean I think that's the big insight then
I mean Heidegger really brings to light
and what and that's directly that space
that's lost and his notion of the tech
that the technology the Age of Mythology
is that he he talks about that what gets
concealed in tech tech not in the
technological way of being right is
concealment itself right we no longer
can can sense in other words it's a it's
kind of a hyper figure izing like the
moment the background is at the moment
it's captured and utilized and
abstracted to the point where the only
thing that we see as real is having
being is that which we can abstract out
of right or ground right so this sense
of the presence of withdrawal or
concealment as a as something that's
actually has being right is the very
thing that's concealed so concealment
its concealing right and that's partly
right the things that makes like we were
talking about earlier about how quickly
there are just huge generational changes
in in what we what designates as
counting as reality right it's in fact
it's happening so fast that it's almost
it's hard to even for the previous
generation to conceive of that that
something's different right right
because it's such a drastic change but
but it's all all the change is when you
step back from when you look at it it's
uncanny in its weirdness right but what
makes it so uncanny is that it doesn't
Deker is uncanny like that's the thing
that's I think that loop of where where
you don't know like it the the you have
these life-changing you know inventions
that happen like our phone and within
like a maze you don't notice it anymore
and yet you're shaped and fashioned by
it but that in fashioning of of it
actually conceals it right so it's it's
so interesting so this is one of the
things I write that I I'm excited and I
think the reason why I keep getting
excited about what we're doing here is
that it seems like the Socratic
dialogues are in some sense a you know
if there's anybody that can hold open
concealment right and almost kind of
torture you hmm
right Socrates right the right Huggle
and he's he's holding open the aperture
for the rest of us yeah so the light can
come through yeah so there's a like the
cave from the mouth of the cave as it
were-- right so this kind of just
interesting to think about this like we
here we are we're you and I are gonna
read these dialogues that are 2,000
years old or something over that and
it's they're inherently gonna not be
immediately entertaining right it's in
fact or yeah sort of entertaining and
it's gonna be a struggle and it's not
gonna make sense right
yet imagining
people encountering this and following
along it's probably gonna strike it it's
it's it's gonna it's gonna be so foreign
to even see that is valuable right yeah
I think so but but they're in it in some
way it's kind of like the opposite of
technology in that sense it's not
collapsing distances it's it's actually
wisdom finding wisdom right in precisely
what isn't immediately useful or
immediately intelligible but right but
but in a certain sense that sense of
being you know zeroing in on the figure
and in those moments opening the ground
in which was concealed and in realizing
that going through that whole process
that did that that the ground flashes
forth right and that's something like
the cultivation or the attunement to
wisdom right is really becoming rare and
rare and rare to even see that kind of
process as virtuous yeah is yeah is
really going away at a level that it's
hard to even see that's right that's
exactly that's well put and and I think
part of part of that is the we're so
unappreciative of ignorance our own
ignorance I mean we sometimes appreciate
ignorant and other people if it if it if
it seems to vindicate our own or or we
seem you know all the more smug by
comparison or something like that but
but are being unappreciative of our own
ignorance I think is a particularly that
we've lost to be able to look out that
escape of knowledge knowing that you're
not equal to it but having a sense of
trust
even something promissory a sense of
trust that with the time and energy and
and a certain discipline that you might
actually being able to you might
actually be able to traverse this gate
right to to appreciate that
appreciation in advance of acquisition
is I think a particular virtue of
pedagogy that I think has largely been
forgotten and lost right and it's and
it's most important in areas domains of
knowledge domains of knowing that are
not immediately comprehensible such as
those that we've brought here to our
table philosophy first and foremost
chiefly and of course religion and
theology etc I sometimes you know the
the hastening to the presumption of
knowledge that happens it's like
systemically and and very in so commonly
in education settings to say we're going
to sit down and we're going to read this
and the hastening to comprehension is
something that educators I think are
just as guilty for to say you know we're
going to have this session and you're
going to expect to understand this after
a period of study after a period of
reading when in fact nothing could be
further from the truth
right if we are if you're if you're made
to subscribe to the notion that you can
acquire this knowledge expeditiously or
within a bounded period of time you're
going to lose interest and you're going
to lose humility in one fell swoop why
is this with my time and why is this
worth why is this worth my well you know
what why should i humble myself before
something that is so finite and
foreclosed to me right you know and I
think that's a spammy that's true of the
study of philosophy but I think it's
more even more true of anything anything
that anything that approaches theology
or studies of religion there's a there's
a there's a presumption that this can be
digested swiftly and it's like no no it
can't no you need to sit with this and
that's where that's the important that's
where the importance of gnosis comes in
as a as a reframing of the definition of
knowing that's why gnosis is so
important because the experiential the
experiential imperative hypnosis the ad
the that the conformity of knower to the
being known that gnosis implies
it comes comes with a premeditation of
humility because until you are absorbed
into what you claim to know you do not
know it and so yeah that just that that
lack of appreciation in every sense of
the term as a way of foreclosing domains
that are voluminous but that seem at
their surface negligible you know place
as Heidegger would say I seek you to
move from confusion hopefully to being
utterly perplexed yes yes exactly
I don't want to relieve your confusion
but I want to move you from confusion to
being perplexed exactly exactly I want
to induce your disorientation so that
you acquire an appetite for orientation
that's fuller and more appreciative and
once I do that then maybe I'll have laid
the conditions for something
approximating an education yeah that's
that's the Socratic and that's the
Socratic project - right that's the
whole the whole purpose of the a
piratical like this is to deprive people
of their propositional certainty so that
their knowing can be transmuted into an
experiential domain that is
fundamentally without the comforts of
certitude totally and almost have a
awaken the eros the desire for for
exactly for that which you don't
understand by exactly like the eros eros
possessed of eros both as a lack and as
an appetite yeah right yes yeah that is
[Laughter]
that's great I'm glad we're doing this
yes likewise so should we Josh at least
article let's crack on the article so
here's here's my thinking and we can do
this however you however you like I
should say maybe for anyone who might be
watching that we attempted this the
other day but my internet connection was
so sluggish that we had to abandon the
project abort the mission
but
we're giving this another try so maybe I
think maybe what we'll do is I can start
reading it and and then you know you can
maybe just stop me whenever you want to
stop and sort of start to start to
annotate or start to yes to sort of
prompt with with any any questions and
that kind of thing how did how does that
sound what do you think sounds great and
what I'll do is I'll upload this to a
Google Doc so people can access it and
read along if they want with us okay
yeah I think we said this in the last
video but I should probably repeat the
fact that this is a this is a draft
chapter a contribution to an anthology
on an anthology of meta modernism which
is to say sort of that a project of
cultural reorientation is what I
understand it to be my understanding is
very abridged though I'm not a meta
modern per se and I shouldn't be taken
as a representative but my sense is it's
sort of a it's it's a it's a it's a
collection of exploratory attitudes or
inquiries that are trying to take some
of the more relevant criticisms of
post-modernism seriously but also
harkening back to to traditions you know
and seating traditions of antiquity that
still have the capacity to inform us and
to not think of those as simply failed
and defunct projects so it's just your
back and the gesture forward
simultaneously that's my sense of what
my mom met a modernism is in a nutshell
anyway so that's kind of a little bit of
setting that to the side this is this is
a chapter that's contributing to an
anthology of that those kinds of
exploratory provocations I guess you
could call them by John Verve a key and
I and it's still in review so it could
change yeah thought I was my disclaimer
totally my thought about I thought it
would be great my idea was to read this
first before to set context to bring to
so much of that paper is about
the dialogues of Plato and particularly
the Socratic dialogue owes that you
describe there as a unnecessary
necessary to to situate us in our times
right and right thank you it really
brings it down into
takes it out of you know ancient
abstraction right - actually the it's
perhaps more pertinent than it's ever
been
[Music]
I'm gonna put it on pause cuz I need to
grab some water okay and we can start
with the zoom okay we're recording okay
you want to go ahead and start reading
and then I'll just sure read and then
I'll just kind of stop you at sir just
interject as you as you see fit
absolutely okay okay and yeah and and
like interject with comments to a guy
like a lot of I mean as we go along one
hopes we've done our job properly then a
lot of the nomenclature a lot of sort of
the definitional work has done in the
paper itself so I'll try I'll try to
avoid being redundant you know when as
we're annotating from without but but if
like you want to interject with just
comments or anything you go ahead okay
great okay so the title of the chapter
the gnosis and the second person
responding to the meaning crisis and the
Socratic quest of authentic dialogue and
this is by John for Venky and myself and
there's a there's a quote to open the
paper which is a quote from Platina
snowing is the organ fitted to the
object
quite simply okay and then there's some
acknowledgments and I'll make note of
the acknowledgments cuz they're
particularly relevant right now the
author's extend warm thanks to guys
thanks doc and Jordan Hall your
midwifery was invaluable in the delivery
of these arguments and your dialogic
partnership is evidence of the spiritual
survival of Plato's Academy and so
anyone who has seen our our four-way
dialogo EB
you're you and I and John and Jordan
hall will implicitly know right that
reference and and I think I just by
reading the paper I will have
demonstrated why those acknowledgments
are so well deserved right
and I'll put on email all of us for the
next one perfect perfect okay so this is
divided into a few parts the first part
is called dialectic and the four ways of
knowing the introduction is titled the
postmodern predicament and the loss of
the second person it now seems obvious
even trite to say that modern
sociability has lost its art of
conversation post-modernism has long
embraced a diffused normativity and
western culture is an endless
vivisecting of tribal fragments mitosis
of single-celled identities inflating
their certitudes to systems of
signification awash and parochial
meanings then our instruments for
meaning making seem untuned by the
common discourse as if we lacked the
forms of interaction that allowed us to
concert' projects of authentic and
collective development the loss of
authentic dialogue is a peculiar oblique
OD of our ethos where the convictions of
knowing pen delayed between subjective
first-person and objective first person
third person rather ontology x' until
they become idols of egoic possession
that we trade defend and brandish for
identity this idolatrous knowing has
atomized our senses of self space-time
and community and has a subsisting and
stillborn encounters unwed bimodal
confusions of relating that is by the
halving of relations over a being in
relation to the world the pre-modern
world might be unavailable but the
postmodern world is in frangible we need
only look to the tenor of public debate
debate to see that the state of
discourse is afflicted with performative
contradictions and victories of self
defeat a despairing desire to be as a
part but only by prevailing in triumph
the self-defeating discourse is but one
pathology of the modern meaning crisis
and the one to which this chapter will
attempt a concerting response the
response begins with a proposal that
discussion like any cardinal virtue is a
technique a craft that can be fostered
or frittered when foster discussion can
become the logos a practice of Anto
intimation there's your word guy that
discursive lee that discursive lee
disciplines are existential attitudes by
arranging our loves to seek self
transformation in the authentic by the
way stay tuned in because until
information is a very sexy word okay so
I should I should say maybe I'll
interpose myself into this for a moment
on to intimation is a term fill up
phosphorus sometimes I'm not not calling
myself a philosopher and saying this but
philosophers tend to take liberties by
by constructing diction in order to
accommodate more complex concepts and
that that involves portmanteaus and a
lot of other creative liberties so John
and I very knowingly and took took a
little bit of a creative and a
philosophic Liberty in this term Anto
intimation trying to capture and enfold
a lot of things that are otherwise not
conjunctive together in this one term so
hopefully it will become evident why
that particular hyphenated combination
is is descriptive in this case okay in
the authentic discourse you cannot know
without also being known cannot be known
without also being changed and cannot be
changed without changing your capacity
to know this second-order appreciation
becomes a developmental imperative de
lobos is among other things a socialized
training and self transcendence and in
the Socratic tradition it was cultivated
in the second person with a pedagogical
that cared for your authentic soul and
taught you to care and the character of
his knowing this chapter will argue at
the meta modern quick us to rediscover
authentic dialogue begins with this
pedagogy and that by typology in the
ways of our knowing we can begin to
adapt the praxis of Socratic dialogue
goes back into common discourse
fortuitously the emergence of 4e
cognitive science which is to say
embodied
embedded in active and extended as a
yielded new theories of extended mind
distributed cognition and the emergence
with psycho technologies socialized
systems a representation that bootstrap
metacognition and allow us to
enculturate forms of second-order
thinking these psycho technologies have
equipped us to disambiguate the process
of knowing to formulate accounts of
intelligence rationality and wisdom to
mobilize a response to the meaning
crisis a new form of authentic
dialoguing will be will be incomplete
without a comprehending system of
propositions enacted by procedures
embodied by perspectives embedded in
participation a system of participatory
knowing can up the dialogic Western
intelligence individual and collective
into rationality and rationality into
wisdom
inspired by the Socratic complete onic
tradition we will refer to this
fostering system of knowing as the
dialectic this investigation into
Socratic platonic dialectic is intended
as a motivating model and cognitive
template for critically explicate in
elucidating and encouraging the emerging
practices of authentic discourse and
relating right this is um so I just want
to highlight from pull this out because
I think one of the big things that I
really got out of this so these are its
first two opening paragraphs is just I
really love the way that you formulated
the problem right in in in that there's
you know if we say that there's you know
first person present right then there's
second musician other right and then
there's like kind of the gods idea or
the third third perspective and that if
you just think about it that there's
something that's going on in our time
where where this sense of the second
person right is gone so all we're left
with is this is this the third like
these these ideologies in many respects
about one objectively true right and my
perspective and how I do or don't fit in
it and how you do or don't fit in it but
it's the elimination of prop seeing as
process which is a little bit like what
we were talking about I think it's at
that that sense in which
we're seeing it like this particular
generation doesn't really have doesn't
understand or presuppose the distinction
of character right we're care usually
defined by having gone through a process
doing hard things going through and that
you developed through a process of
having lived for a long time and you end
up knowing things that you couldn't have
known earlier and and so they're in a
certain in a certain way there's and
also I really like the thing that you
said about that quality of I think where
you could see that this a lot is that I
am based on my identity right my ID you
know all of this like extreme talk about
like you know you know ethnic ethnic
identities cultural identities that
there's this kind of this sense of that
there's these pre-given things that you
are either a part of our enough a part
of right right they that they're that
they're unquestionable like that they
are they are as they are in that sense
of that you become through a process or
engagement it is losing its kalos for us
right so in some ways you're kind of
setting up the problem of like well you
know let's let's actually return back to
dialogue let's return how one becomes
becomes through the relation becomes who
one is through it and beyond it mm-hmm
yes well put very well put all right all
right Shh shall I continue
yes okay so the next section is called
the dialectic vocabulary logos gnosis
and rationality
it is increasingly difficult to invoke
the Socratic and platonic traditions
without sinking to the quagmire of
modern lexicology terms like knowledge
reason and rationality had been dulled
by the abrasions of materialism
Enlightenment thinkers abridged
epistemic from the original
understanding or inter standing to fact
acquisition rationality from the Latin
arathi Oh too dispassionate logic ality
and logos to univocal purpose such
notional astigmatism czar culpable for
many modern cul-de-sacs an inherent an
inheritance of obsolete epistemologies
premise omeka refracted accounts of
knowing suffice to say I met a modern
rehabilitation of any of the above is no
small undertaking and in a fit of
aspiration this chapter will endeavor it
will endeavor to model the
rehabilitation in addition to arguing
for it the use of the term aspiration
here is technical determined by Agnes
Callard to mean a proleptic rationality
not calculative arguments but a
cultivated view from above that changes
the identity of a subject as he comes to
know he could not imagine knowing and so
comes to be whom he could not imagine
being this self transcendence requires a
notion of rationality that emphasizes
the amelioration of self-deception the
affordance of aspiration and the
subordination of argumentation to the
Telos of personal transformation
dialectical reasons that quote a man who
has learned anything becomes in each
case such as his knowledge makes him and
quote from the gorgeous plato's gorgeous
and to this end aspirations the
deployment of attention to our epistemic
maturation the view from above as a
relation we adopt to raise us as we go
to understand it philosophy in the
tradition of Socrates was a dialectic
system for practicing proleptic
rationality the loving of wisdom so
defined put us in a relation of
wondering aspiration so would that be
wondering aspiration in inter standing
and in interesting words like inter
standing philosophy a-- practicing
prophylactic rationality is another
great word who
laughter elliptic rationality and that's
that's calories term that's collards
term that that John John has adapted
into some of his videos and lectures and
we've adapted into this work because it
because it it it it gives breath to the
definition of rationality such that it's
able to accommodate the character ology
that you were just describing what is
rational often times is not simply a
kind of a kind of dispassionate
calculation at any given moment in time
but as what is ultimately rational by
this mark latronnik definition is
whatever will whatever will lay the
conditions for one's transformation such
that we will become more and more
accommodating and adaptive to experience
and more able to flourish through it
right and so what is rational then
becomes whatever will change us and
regather us around ever deeper and more
encompassing problems right which makes
it which relates back to the idea of
gnosis right the conformed knowing
having to regather re having to be
reconstituted around the objects of your
attention around the objects of their
knowing and I mean object in a in an
obstructive sense they don't mean object
in in a material sense right that would
be something like that would be
something like you know when you're
sensing into something and you have a
hunch or something grabs your attention
but you don't know you don't know um
what it is but it still grabs you it's
like there's the horizon and then
there's the the thing that draws you
towards the horizon right mm-hmm
where it's in to what you were saying is
that this is a it's Socrates attunes
attention right and the relations to
continually look for what it can't make
object right right for what it kicks
that's a great way of putting it for
what it can't yet to make object to
tend to what it can't yet make object I
mean by analogy white we might say and
buy a mallet by analogy is not a
dismissal quite the contrary and that'll
become obvious in the next section we
talk a little bit more about analogy the
role of the analog but by analogy we
might think of it as I'm taking this as
a sort of a Vygotsky an example that
John uses quite often about the
relationship between the parent and the
child then the child obeys the wishes of
the parent not because the child can
rationalize himself around those
decisions because the child can't
rationalize himself or herself around
the parents decisions because they they
encompass variables and dimensions of
experience that are foreign and as yet
unknown to the child so the child isn't
the child isn't beholden to the wishes
of the parent because the child has
reasoned his way around their problem in
any comprehensible sense right the
parents rationality in adopting to the
to the to the to the wishes of the
parent is a deeper deeper and proleptic
kind of trust right now I'm not now
there's obviously there's there's more
there's more at play in the in the in
the child's obedience to the parent then
proleptic rationality but but but that's
what I mean by it being an analogy that
imagine the child's did the trust that
the child entrusts the parent because
the perspective of the parent is
completely super-sis of to the
perspective of the child yeah right and
and so entrusting to the superordinate
'iv even if your own perspective can't
quite it isn't ultimately you
it's sort of if it's if it's beyond your
your your ken as it were your your still
you're entrusting yourself to something
that's yeah that can that can contain a
perspective that you're not able to
contain yes and that you can ration you
can have a relationship to that which
you can't totally understand but it can
glow to you in such a way that it grants
the normativity of rationing right and
so that would be an example the
parent-child relationship and it seems
it seems like it would also be something
about when you're just getting to know
somebody who fall in love with them
right there's that quality of
inexhaustible mnestheus somebody that
they're so much more than in it there's
an awareness in fact the in love the
erotic impulse of diving in is seems to
be directly related to that there's so
much more than I can actually see right
yes right
yeah ranking and the enactment of the
following in love and moving towards you
are all in some sense that that sense of
what's beyond when I can see but I can
write be constituted by it yeah right
right yeah your intra mural trusting
yourself to the depths that are sure to
transform you yeah right and that marks
I mean that's Kierkegaard talked talked
about that a little bit when he talks
but is sort of his night of the idea of
the night of faith right that at some
point you reach a threshold beyond which
you can no longer reliably gather and
retrieve a concrete normativity and so
then the the process of the ontological
entrusting that you have to place in in
what is in what is unbounded is sort of
a it's it's an it's an inevitable part
of of the process of self transcendence
to transformation and and and that also
is what makes it subject to
self-deception as well right
understanding when to entrust yourself
to the incomprehensible debts right
right and then it beyond which you don't
can no longer see clearly is it's
precisely the question and that's where
the training on the education the
mentorship
right that's why Socrates is the
mediating figure because because
Socrates because Socrates conditions the
trust from you know I mean we're gonna
talk about this later in the paper too
right but from one proposition to
another in a series of graduating steps
Socrates carefully trains the trust and
earns the trust of his interlocutors so
that when he dissolves their dialo goes
into a pariah and moves to effect the
reorientation he has already earned
plausible trust in the trading of
propositions thus far to have his
authority be very rational even if the
move he's making isn't intelligible to
each of the individual participants I
trust you because you've earned my trust
thus far therefore I can plausibly
entrust you with this that I cannot
understand yeah well I did say that
there's a pragmatism there's a tinge of
pragmatism to this as well obviously
yeah and it's a innit yeah well I think
one of the things that just kind of
struck me is is there's a move that
happened inside of me and understanding
this what is if I can't articulate it's
there's one thing and being able to
respond to what's beyond the horizon
that I can't that isn't I can't make
object but then but it's it that's also
could be very self deceptive so it's
another thing to have the wisdom to be
able to another that's fascinating like
they have the wisdom to be able to
apprehend on some level what thing that
I can't make object is the right thing
that will lead me to the like a wise
place like that's there leads a whole
other level of education in it right
it's funny I'm I'm I got I get the sense
of that there's you know one of the
things about our time is like there's a
big loss of mentorship for the idea
right we're right there is it there is
this quality having been mentored myself
there is this quality of where there's
kind of like what they're saying the
Metra saying to you explicitly right
they're telling you you know where to
put your hands and how to do it but
there's this whole other level of like
the way that they're participating with
you and the participation that they're
called that there's like a meta there's
a meta intelligibility to the way that
they use their hands the way the depth
you that are somehow in the background
but end up being the very thing that
gives you the right ability that you
write because later usually a lot later
that you can then attribute it to to
that mentor that mentorship that's right
it's a patient element of it yeah
exactly exactly participate that
participatory element of it is itself
its itself enabled by the dramaturgy of
like the I mean there's there's a reason
why there's a reason there's a there's a
mimetic process in play with these
dialogues right that's the whole idea of
internalizing the sage internalizing the
socratic figure isn't isn't that you're
simply isn't that you've been you've
it's it's not simply that the the mode
of inquiry is conferred on you it's that
the manner and the attitudinal come like
the composure of the inquiry is also
conferred on you and that's why it's so
dramaturgical because you're playing the
role it's the playing of the role that
espouses the training of the wisdom
right it's stepping into of what Falls
of the socratic figure right it's not
simply that you're because you're right
it's something it's something deeper
than whatever whatever straightforward
instruction you're given it's an
attitudinal absorption of the person
yeah that grants you the latitude in
your own identity to be able to assume
and host ever more of their
perspective assume right host Wow
interesting right so playing the role of
Socrates and I mean this godless this
happened and and an artists tend to
report this a lot right I'm thinking of
authors who are writing characters or
actors that are playing a character on
stage often report the fact that when if
they're if they're if they're in the
flow state I should qualify that to say
if they're in the flow state and they're
playing a certain character whether
whether simply giving voice in the
literary medium or actually embodying a
character in a theatrical medium they
find themselves suddenly equipped to
speak with a voice that resounds beyond
their own in other words they can
conceive as the character can conceive
and as they could not outside the bounds
of the character right so there's
something about the process of play and
I mean a lot of people right from Piaget
onward developmentally talked about the
role of this and how important it is and
how indispensable it is but that's one
thing and that's also I mean as if we
need something to dignify and qualify
how vital those kinds of art forms are
to us because the art forms that allow
us to extend identification are the same
artful forms that actually allow us to
condition the sense of play that endow
us with the capacity to seek self
transformation genuinely on
authentically because it prevents the
ossification of identity that happens
when we're constantly vacillating from
the first to the third person if I am
simply an object I own to be possessed
or dispossessed of that I will not be
ever verbalized from without in a way
that seems spontaneous and unanticipated
and it is the spontaneous and
unanticipated emergence of oneself in
the throes of something ritual in the
throes of something poetic and creative
that rebirths the potential of how we
can understand ourselves and anything
large right again the gnosis the gnosis
is inseminated by the play and that's
why the Platonic dialogues or dialogues
that's one of the reasons clearly why
the platonic dialogues are dialogues
because they ritualized the dramaturgy
of role play that is actually necessary
for the acquisition of the Socratic
persona so that we can actually act
through it appropriately yeah that's is
so interesting I just did this thing
about hosting host the role it's like
it's like I can host a party right in a
certain sense like I can host a party
and have people come over that I don't
yet I'm yet not yet capable of I'm not
yet capable of knowing how to host but
in the hosting I'm drawn forth into
realizing conversations and the
intelligibility in like in this way that
I will consciously probably say oh yeah
I learned this I learned that but yet it
will come through at levels that I can
recognize you know after I host parties
after that right there's a sense of
that's right being impregnated with well
the sense of a potential or a
possibility that on some level I can I
can apprehend is worth it to host it yet
the that in some way yes that sense of
the host becomes becomes what's hosted
and that's right you're you are played
by the role that you're also playing you
are played by the role that you're also
playing and that and then the way that
you comport you're you the way that you
comport yourself and your credulity
towards that role yeah I think also
matters because then if you if you have
if you overplay the role as it were or
overdone
over identify yourself with the role
then you get the classic inflation of
the persona that um talks about right
and then if you if you're if you're
endlessly divested from the role and
non-committal and
and and not entreated to play then
you're you're never going to get the
sense of experimentation with your
identity that's all ultimately going to
going to to yield the merchants that you
can then grow into and through and so
it's the simultaneous identity and
decide entity and that's why you're John
and I talked about it as a state of
translucency right that you're seeing
and sing through simultaneously you're
seeing the role and you're seeing
through the role and that means that you
can maintain the tension of that state
of play without completely dissolving
into it and and in a way completely
losing yourself in in it and being
incapable of then exchanging or
extricate yourself from it but you're
also committed enough to be properly
embodied within its analogic functions
and that's why that state of tension
between belief and disbelief
you know identity and dis identity
represented by the idea of being
translucent is so I think so it come
very very essential to this idea yeah so
wow this is great it's great probably
should do maybe one more paragraph and
then okay maybe we should compile it is
probably getting over over an hour and a
half at this point yeah it's gonna I had
a suspicion that with with with I say I
say this with no sugar and whatsoever
but I had a suspicion that it would take
us forever to do this and that's okay
okay one more paragraph it is the loving
of relation the loving of wisdom so
defined put us in a relation of
wondering aspiration okay in philosophy
ax the efficacy of dialectic rationality
is inseparable from its dialogical
format yet the meaning of the Ilocos
requires a more exacting definition of
logos a term like realization is more
commensurate with the etymologies of
logos as a conceptual gathering or
putting in order it refers to a stroll
functional organisation a fitted Nisour
purpose that disposes an efficient
mimetic relation to reality like the
extract of an ontological pattern
applied as a primitive implement the
idea of gathering go ahead guy what what
is when the remind me what mimetic means
mimetic like mimesis which is an
imitation okay okay got it
great yeah applied as a probative
implement the idea of gathering
intelligibility saw some revival among
the pragmatists who proposed that the
meaning of a concept was constituted by
its quote conceivable bearing upon the
conduct of life that's quote from purse
charles purse
for example the pencil is writable or
the chairs citable from any of the
pragmatists logos was a sharpening
approximation of the real that impre--
she ate it in reality a hypothesis that
realized by the texture of an
individual's ongoing contact with the
world which recursively deepened his arm
to logical grasp centuries earlier
Platonists and drew introduced a
similarly tactile metaphor to describe
an enosis a grasping fist that gathers
to its object and tightens into
verisimilitude appreciation there's that
word again
at once meaning gratitude apprehension
and graduation of this grasp is the
function of proleptic rationality now is
that not as applied to knowledge that is
to information but to understanding
which grasps the plausible significance
of information by its relevance to our
aspired possibility proleptic
rationality educates logos through
disciplined discussion to gather itself
around the highest order of potential
for any intelligible unit of knowledge
in other words proleptic rationality has
us appreciate information based on how
the information makes us more rationally
appreciative casts us and deeper
conformity with reality this is the
significance of the dialectic project
appreciating logos with an aspiring
gnosis that espouses shared identity
with unto us being dialectic so hey guys
I just want to read that again because I
there's a lot of cliche here this is the
significance of the dialectic project
pre-shading logos with an aspiring
nosis that espouses shared identity with
Antos being Wow
I know there's a lot this there's a lot
hold it in here longer I start I start
that sentence one person and by the end
I'm someone else
believe me guy I feel the same yes I
can't imagine what it was like to write
that okay cool I appreciate that for a
second
dialectic is the praxis that seeks to
engender and enhance the process of
dialogue owes Socrates advances the
dialectic project by conducing through
dialogue a percipient wedded miss
between the knower and the being known
that becomes a symbolized relation an
embodied binding that affects trans Jeff
loved the Opera nominal logical
continuity between a subject and her
object this is dia logos symbols from
the Greek symbol on adjoin entities into
a shared identity and induce this trans
gently conductor induces an electric one
this current of trans Jack tivity is
participatory it synchronizes the other
ways of knowing into a patterned
similitude this cognitive
synchronization is fundamental to
Plato's philosophy ax if Socrates is the
conductor of knowing his dialogues are
its circuitry dialectic signifies the
quote current that expresses the nature
of truth as concealed as requiring
search in the direction of a self that
is not yet known close quote
that's a better that pay I hope I'm
saying her name right
really incredible books on Socrates and
Plato our aspired continuity with this
yet unknown self and the world it B
holds was symbolized by the Socratic
arrows intimating the apotheosis aspect
of man that would later emerge through
neoplatonism and Christianity in what
Andrew Stein calls our divine double
quote our divine
and I should say it's noted in the paper
itself but I should say John in his
series and awakening from the meeting
crisis has one of his videos more or
less devoted he has also a couple of
conversational videos devoted to this
topic but one of the awakening from the
meaning crisis series is on a
specifically korban and the divine
double or that worthy or the divine in
Corbin calls it an angel I believe is
his idea of the imaginal angel anyway
yeah you want to read the rest of that
paragraph or wait a minute or that
that's that's the end of the paragraph
okay I did it I did as instructed should
I should I keep I don't know should I
stop there what do you think let's see
let's just let's just check it out for a
second so so I think what I'm
appreciating is one to reading this is
one this is really ecstatic to
understand I'm like I'm like reading
this along and I'm feeling like kind of
jolted along and these kind of like you
four years of things coming together so
I what I just want to appreciate the way
that this is written and so there's a
tech there's a technical precision but
it what it gathers so much more than you
can technically account for in the way
there's written so I just really want to
appreciate you for being the kind of
being that you are such that that
something like this gets to exist it's
really great thank you and I think one
of the things that's interesting to me
about this is what what's hitting me is
that there's a I can recognize I can
recognise everything that you're talking
about like it hits a note that's just so
it seems as true and I think that
truth that it it seems to is that
there's a logos to our being right and
our relationship to the world and and
the way the world is and the way I am in
relationship to it that the it's in our
machinery to for this to happen it's
like it's it's hard not to feel it's
very difficult to feel cynical about
reality when you recognize that this can
be possible without you having to
construct it that it's your of it I mean
it's just a it's a it's a sense of trust
and faith I feel in that this is
possible right that's right wonderous
that's right
that's right yeah the idea that it's an
endogenous or intrinsic feature of your
normativity something that simply awaits
your recognition awaits your remembrance
of it is a yeah it's a it's a very
humbling it's a very humbling thing to
to just didn't then the notion of it is
that you're right the notion of it is
ecstatic unto itself because you realize
quite simply that you were you are
beyond yourself you are you are ever
beyond yourself you always have been
beyond yourself and that you are a
relation that that awaits consummation
in some sense and that what it takes to
understand that is the very thing that's
being understood rightly that's that
Hermann etic those circles was ever
evolving circles um it's really really
really great they're just that's right
I just love that I don't know there's
something for me that just like we're
that we're we're that and that seems to
be characteristic of dialo goes and of
these deeper conversations right of yeah
where there is that implicit recognition
that like the very thing that we're
inside of that we didn't notice in like
conceiving of it we recognize that we're
inside of it without having had to know
it right
and there's X right the birth of that
look you know the logos the the
gathering and what's gathered and you
dwell in the get this it's a I just it I
think I'm appreciating why you know why
Heidegger like first tried to go into
this in terms of temporality because
it's totally yeah it's an ecstatic
temporalities so much more apt to
accurately um
reckon with us that our being like that
sign human being right is source not
we're not
got to look at this in terms of an
animai kind of subject in a space that
then acts it's like that stuff just
falls apart when you get when you when
you look at it what is it to actually be
right there's like some level and I
think there's some history to this too
because my understanding this you know
if we say that Hegel was the kind of
culmination of a system right like one
of the things that you Hannes I've
appreciated about johannes is like how
he says like look you can't that you
can't add anything to Hegel system right
and no no no it's immaculate it's a
matter yeah and it's almost the
culmination of the actual trumping the
possible and right in in a sense it
missus right conceals right and so in
some way there's a there's a sense of
slipping that back out and if we say no
way but possible is what animates yes
live to be way more animates animates is
the perfect word for it right it's the
imbuing with Animas the imbuing with
soul it's the gilding it's the it's it's
the it's the enchantment of actuality by
possibility added curricular costs cause
it's something like a transubstantiation
of experience that the way in which
we read actuality it's a it's the it's
the it's the kind of phenomenological
literacy that we're trying to retrain
and re-educate so that we read into
actuality with a perspective that
enchants it's being so good so good so
glad we're doing this as am i as am i
all right my friend
so this is our first official well it's
not our first official video but it's
the first one yeah thing together all
right
first one we're not just talking about
doing it I'll post this and I'll make
sure and do a little video beforehand to
set up some context and okay yeah okay
and hopefully hopefully when we come to
do the next one I'm not going to have to
pilfer Internet I'll actually have it at
home boy what a saga it's been anyway
thank you for being patient with me yes
as I as I wrestle with technology
absolutely it's the patient with you and
it's nice to be Co patience with each
other all right thank you my friend look
doc you soon bye